Your DNA is probably already in a database.
你的DNA可能已经在一个数据库当中了
You didn't have to provide a sample or give consent
你无需提供样本或者给予许可
but the unique sequence
但四种碱基（A、T、G和C）的独特序列
of As, Ts, Gs and Cs that make you you
are searchable nonetheless.
使你依然可以被检索
So if you committed a heinous crime
所以，如果你犯下了令人发指的罪行
and left a bit of your DNA,
并留下了你哪怕只有一点的DNA
law enforcement could search it in a database
执法部门就可以在数据库中对你的DNA进行检索
and identify you.
并最终识别到你的身份
This video includes a discussion of serious crimes
本视频包括一些可能令观众感到不安的严重罪行的讨论
which may be disturbing for some viewers
so I wanted to let you know that upfront,
所以我想提前告知您
but I think it's necessary
但由于显而易见的原因
to talk about these crimes in some detail
我认为有必要详细讨论这些犯罪
for reasons that will become apparent.
In the small town of Visalia, California in the mid 1970s,
1970年代中期，在加利福尼亚州维塞利亚小镇
one of the state's most prolific criminals got his start.
该州犯罪最多的罪犯之一开始了他的犯罪生涯
He repeatedly broke into houses and stole small items
他多次闯入民宅并偷走现金、硬币和珠宝等小物件
like cash, coins, and jewelry.
He was dubbed the Visalia ransacker
他被称为“维塞利亚劫掠者”
but soon his crimes escalated.
但很快他的罪行就不止于此了
- Six months later in 1976,
六个月后的1976年
he moves up to Sacramento and over
他搬去了萨克拉门托
the course of the next three years,
并且在接下来的三年里
he's moving all across Northern California
他在北加州多地犯下了了超过50起强奸案
committing numerous sexual assaults,
over 50 sexual assaults.
- Here, he was called the east area rapist.
在这里，他被称为“东区强暴魔”
- [Male Reporter] The police are saying lock up tight.
警察说要锁紧门窗
Sacramento's infamous east area rapist may still be in town.
因为萨拉克门托臭名昭著的“东区强暴魔”可能还在城里
- And then in 1979, he moves down to Southern California,
然后在1979年，他搬去南加州
starting in Santa Barbara and starts killing.
从圣巴巴拉开始杀人
And he was known as the original night stalker
他被称为南加州的“暗夜尾行者”
in Southern California.
- [Reporter] Variously known as the east area rapist
他被人们称为“东区强暴魔”“暗夜尾行者”
and the original night stalker,
these were brutal meticulously planned crimes
这些是1976年至1986年间跨越加利福尼亚州多县之间精心策划的残酷犯罪
that spanned numerous California counties
between 1976 and 1986.
- Police believed that all of these crimes
警察相信所有这些罪行都是由现在被称为“金州杀手”的同一人所犯
were committed by the same person
now known as the golden state killer.
How was it known that these were committed
如何知道这些都是由同一人所犯的呢？
by the same person?
- Investigators were relying on MO.
调查人员们依赖MO
MO, modus operandi is basically
MO，作案手法，基本上可以理解为犯罪分子是如何犯罪的
how a criminal will commit a crime.
- He was wearing some type of a mask or a hood.
他戴着某种面具或者兜帽
He was wearing shorts and a T-shirt.
他穿着短裤和T恤衫
- The golden state killer had a very distinctive MO
“金州杀手”有一个非常独特的MO
- What he would do is
他会做的是
he would break into a house with a gun,
他会持枪闯入一栋有男人和女人的民宅
a house with a man and a woman.
He would tie them up
他会把他们绑起来
tell the man I'm gonna put plates on your back.
然后告诉那个男人，我要把盘子放到你的后背上
If I hear those plates move,
如果我听到盘子动了
I'm going to kill your wife and then kill you,
我就要杀了你的妻子然后再杀了你
take the wife into another room and sexually assault her.
他把妻子带到另一个房间对她进行性侵犯
Then he would go through the house for however much time,
然后他会在房子里徘徊相当久
eating, stealing stuff, stealing little things or whatever
就吃东西，偷东西之类的
and then he would leave.
然后他才会离开
- How was he not caught based on fingerprint evidence?
他怎么没因为指纹证据被抓？
- Well, he didn't leave his fingerprints.
好吧，他没留下指纹
He always wore a mask.
他总是戴着面具
He always had gloves on.
他总是戴着手套
This was an offender that did everything
这是一个竭尽全力防止自己被抓的罪犯
to prevent himself from being caught.
- [Reporter] The golden state killer has been linked
金州杀手与在加州发生的至少12起谋杀案、50起强奸案和一系列的盗窃案有关
to at least 12 murders, 50 rapes
and a string of burglaries throughout California.
- All right, how's it going?
最近怎么样？
- How you doing? - Good.
你好吗？ 好的好的
- So we supply DNA sequencing solutions
我们为处理犯罪现场DNA的法医实验室提供DNA测序解决方案
to the forensic laboratories that process crime scene DNA.
At a crime scene, there's typically less than a nanogram
一般我们在犯罪现场，只能找到不到1纳克的DNA并且它们通常还会降解，对吧？
纳克：10的-9次方克
of DNA left and it's usually degraded, right?
So it breaks down.
所以它降解了
- Why is there so little? at a crime scene?
为什么在犯罪现场，只有这么少？？？
A nanogram?
只有1纳克？
- Yes.
对的
- That's insane.
这太疯狂了
- Yes.
对啊
- There's no accident that he stops in 1986.
他在1986年停止作案绝非偶然
1986 is when the first DNA case of a murder case
1986年是第一个谋杀案的第一起DNA案件解决的年份
is actually solved with DNA and he's,
第一次用DNA解决的，嗯..他...
I think he's following that and he's saying, you know what,
我觉得他正在跟进这些案件的进度，他说，你知道吗
what I'm doing here, I'm leaving my DNA.
我在这做的事，会遗留下我的DNA
I can't do this anymore.
我可再也不能犯罪了
- [Reporter] Investigator Paul Holes tracked
调查员保罗·霍尔斯追查了“金州杀手”几十年
the golden state killer for decades.
- He couldn't account for DNA technology
他不了解DNA技术
and that really was his big mistake.
这确实是他犯下的大错
That was the critical mistake.
这是一项严重的错误
He left his DNA all over California.
他把他的DNA留得整个加州到处都是
And it turns out that in three of the cases,
事实证明，在其中三个案例中
I had three sexual assault kits and that's where I got
我有三个性侵工具包，这就是我从北加州获得“金州杀手”DNA的地方
性侵工具包：一种取证工具，能帮助受害者快速留下被性侵证据
单核苷酸多态性：DNA序列中单个核苷酸的替代导致的、且分布于种群中相当一部分个体（如：1%以上）中的基因多样性。
the golden state killer's DNA from Northern California.
- But having the unknown killer's DNA wasn't enough.
但只有未知杀手的DNA还不够
They needed to match it to a known sample.
他们还需将其与已知样本匹配起来
In 1990, the FBI started work on
1990年，FBI(美国联邦调查局)
what would become a national genetic database.
开始建立全国的基因库
It mainly stores DNA profiles
这个基因库主要记录已被判刑的罪犯
from convicted criminals and persons of interest.
和案件相关人士的DNA档案
It's called the combined DNA index system
它被称为“联合DNA索引系统”，
or CODIS for short.
缩写是CODIS
In each of your cells, there are 23 pairs of chromosomes,
你的每一个细胞中，都有23对染色体
one from your mom and one from your dad.
一对染色体中有一条来自母亲，另一条来自父亲
And at particular places on some chromosomes,
在某些染色体中的特定位置上
there are short sections of DNA that repeat
会有一些重复的DNA片段，
like A A T G, A A T G, A A T G, and so on.
像是AATG,AATG,AATG这样
These are called short tandem repeats or STRs
这些片段被称为“短串联重复序列（STR）”
and different people have different numbers of repeats.
不同的人有不同数量的重复片段
Forensic labs produce STR profiles
法医实验室通过计算所有的重复片段总数
by counting up the number of repeats at each location.
来生成STR档案。
Initially, there were only 13 places on the DNA
最初，DNA上只有13个位置的STR会被计数
where STRs were counted, but in 2017
但到了2017年
that was expanded to 20.
这个数量扩大到了20个
It feels to me like that's not that much information.
我感觉这个档案并没有提供太多有用的信息
- It isn't.
-不，并不是你认为的这样
- But the chances of two people having
两个人在所有被计算的位置上，
the exact same number of repeats at all locations
都拥有相同数量的重复片段的概率
is incredibly small.
是非常小的
The CODIS database now contains
现在，CODIS数据库中，
over 18 million STR profiles.
已经有了超过1800万的STR档案
- The golden state killer's DNA profile has been up
2001年，金州杀手的DNA档案
at the national DNA database
就被上传到了
that's run by the FBI called CODIS since 2001
FBI建立的国家DNA数据库（CODIS）
and has been searching ever since with no hits.
自那以后，就一直在找他，但毫无成效
We did Interpol searching,
我们向国际刑警组织申请
trying to search other country's DNA databases thinking
尝试在其他国家的DNA数据库中搜索，想着
well, maybe he came from a out of the country
好吧，用了这么长时间都能没确认他的身份的原因
that's why after all this time we have yet
to be able to identify him
可能是因为他来自其他国家
and obviously we didn't get any hits.
不过很显然，我们的搜索没有任何收获
- But genetic sequencing technology was advancing rapidly.
尽管如此，基因测序技术依然发展迅猛
- [Female Reporter] The human genome project was completed.
[女记者]人类基因组计划已经完成
Since 1986 scientists had been mapping and sequencing
从1986年开始，科学家们就一直在
the three billion nucleotides contained
绘制和测序人类基因组中的
in the human genome.
30亿个核苷酸
It's anticipated that
这很让人期待……
- Soon private companies began offering genetic tests
- 很快，私人公司们就开好似直接给客户们提供基因测试的项目
directly to consumers and they provide far more genetic data
并向CODIS数据库直接提供更多的基因数据
than what's in the CODIS database.
I traveled to Houston, Texas
我去到德州的波士顿，去拜访「家族族谱DNA公司」的总部
to visit Family Tree DNA headquarters.
- We'll go in the lab and we'll start talking
我们会进到实验室并就一个样本的生命周期进行探讨。
about the life cycle of a sample.
There you go.
给你
- Thank you.
谢谢
These samples, what are they?
这些是什么的样本？
- So they're cheek cells. They just scrape
这些是脸部的细胞
the inside of their cheek, they put a cap on it
人们就只是在他们的脸颊里面刮一下，用盖子盖上然后就送回给我们。
and they send it back to us.
- It's like a robot ballet.
- 它就像芭蕾舞机器人一样
- Yes, so for DNA extraction,
- 是的，DNA提取也是如此
we need to remove all of the protections that are on the DNA
我们要移除DNA上面的保护层然后它自己就会分离出来
and just separate it by itself so we can do testing on that.
这样我们就能在它上面进行测试
- Instead of looking at 20 places on your DNA,
- 我们并不仅仅测试你DNA中的20个地方
these tests examined 700 to 800,000.
而是测试700到80万个
- The Family Finder test is based
- 寻找家人的(基因)测试是基于一个叫做微阵列的方式
on what's called a micro array
and this is what a micro array looks like.
这就是微阵列看起来的样子
Each one of those boxes is an individual.
每一个这种格子都是一个人
We can fit 24 individuals on here.
我们能在这一片上放24个人
And within that box is about 710,000 positions
那在这个格子里面是我们正在检查，从中获取数据的
of your DNA, that we're measuring, we're getting data for.
你DNA中大约71万个位置
- 710,000?
71万个？
- Yes, and they're called snips.
对，他们叫片段。
- So hang on, that's like 710,000
所以 等等 这里就是71万个片段，就像ATGC那样？
individual bases, like ATGC?
- Yes.
是的
- For each person, you can measure 24 on that single chip?
对于每一个人，您可以在这一个芯片上检查24个片段？
- Correct.
是的
- The human genome consists of three billion bases.
人的基因组中包含有300亿个碱基
All people share about 99.9% the exact same DNA,
而所有人类的DNA中有99.9%是完全相同的
which means on average, only about three million basis
这意味着平均来说，人与人之间的基因只有300万个位置有差异
differ from person to person.
These individual letter changes are known
这种单个核酸的改变被称为单核苷酸多态性(SNPs)
as single nucleotide polymorphisms or SNPs.
So on there, are there a whole bunch
所以在这里就有一大堆那些小片的DNA那样吗？
of like little pieces of DNA then?
- Yes, so what we have is a short piece of DNA
是的 我们这里的一个小片的DNA 就是特定的一个多态单核苷酸
that is specific to one SNP.
So it's one position in the genome
所以这是我们能知道的基因组内的一个能造成差异的位置
where we know there can be a difference.
- Okay.
这样
Is there any example of a simple SNP
能给我一个简单的单核苷酸多态性的例子吗？
that confers some sort of?
- Actually blue eyes is a single base change.
实际上蓝色眼睛是一个单基位的变化
- Really?
真的？
- Yeah.
是的
- So everyone with blue eyes has this one letter change? - mm hmm
所以每一个有蓝眼睛的人都有这一个单基位变化？ - 嗯哼
- You can see now it's starting to scan the first box.
现在你能看到它从第一个格子开始扫描
- The results of your 710,000 SNPs can tell you
你的71万个多态单核苷酸能让你知道你的地域性祖先或者潜在的医疗状况。
about your geographic ancestry
or possible medical conditions,
but they can also quantify
但它们也可以量化你和某个人的血缘关系程度。
how related you are to someone else.
The genetics of having a kid
产生后代的遗传学过程
are a bit like cutting two decks of cards together.
有点像把两沓扑克牌切在一起
The resulting deck will share
由此得到的后代
about half its cards with each parent
与最初的两沓分别共享一半的卡牌
and there'll be long sequences of cards
于是新牌堆中会有
which match identically sequences in each parent.
与父母一方完全相同的序列
Now, if this deck has a kid, well then its offspring
现在如果这堆牌有一个孩子 这个孩子会有
will share only about a quarter of its cards
大约四分之一的卡牌分别来自（外）祖父（母）中的一个
with each grandparent and the sections of identical cards
而相同卡牌组成的部分将会变得更短
will be shorter, and this is how it works with DNA.
这些规则也对DNA适用
The more closely you're related to someone,
你与某人的血缘关系越近
the more DNA you share and the longer
你们共有的DNA就越多
the blocks of identical DNA are.
相同的 DNA 片段越长
But to compare the DNA of two people,
但是要比较两个人的DNA
you don't need to read every letter.
你不必遍历每一个碱基
The snips are sprinkled throughout the DNA
SNP 在 DNA 中散布
roughly every 2000 bases.
大约每 2000 个碱基出现一次
So if you find long sections where the snips match up,
所以如果你发现 SNP 在一个长片段里对得上
you can bet that the DNA in between is identical too
就可以认为两段 DNA 也完全相同
by comparing hundreds of thousands of snips sprinkled
通过比较成百上千
throughout the DNA,
散布在 DNA 中的 SNP
you can see where these identical blocks start and stop
你可以找到相同片段的起止点
and so how much total DNA is shared.
从而得知由多少 DNA 是共有的
- Everywhere that is highlighted in blue
- 随处可见用蓝色标出的就是
is where I share DNA.
我共有的 DNA
- With your father? - With my father
- 和你的父亲 - 和我的父亲
which is exactly what you expect
和预期的情况一样
because I should share DNA with him everywhere
我和他应该在各处都有相同的基因片段
because he gave me 50% of my DNA.
因为我遗传了他一半基因
So this is a second to third cousin.
这是我的从兄弟或再从兄弟
I have no idea who this person is.
我不知道这个人是谁
And you can see here,
你会发现
we are definitely not as closely related as me and my dad
我们之间的血缘关系当然不像我和我父亲那样近
because where the blue is,
因为这些蓝色区域
those are the only regions of the chromosome
我们仅在这些染色体区域
where we share DNA.
有相同的基因
- We all know that these genetic tests
我们都知道这些遗传学检测
can help identify our relatives but the question is,
可以帮助我们找到亲属 但问题是
can you do the same thing with law enforcement databases?
你能用执法者的数据库做到相同的事吗
Can you identify family members using the CODIS database?
您能用 CODIS 数据库辨认家庭成员吗
- You can and it's only limited
能 但不完全能
to really first order and second order relatives.
它只限于第一代和第二代亲属
- That means if I'm looking for the golden state killer,
这意味着如果我要寻找金州杀手
I'm looking for either his father, his brother or his son.
我是在找他的父亲 他的兄弟或者他的儿子
We did that over and over again with no hits.
我们这样做了多次却一无所获
- Why is it so limited?
- 为什么它如此受限
- Because you've only got 23 loci.
- 因为你只检查23个基因位点
If you wanna do proper kinship analysis,
如果你想进行更好的血缘分析
you need to have more points assessed on that genome
你需要测定基因组上的更多位置
to see how related you really are.
才能知道亲缘远近
- We know the answer is behind a locked door
- 我们知道答案在一扇上锁的门后
and the answer is behind the locked door
答案在 23andMe 和 Ancestry.com
of 23andMe and Ancestry.com.
的数据库中
We know that they have millions of profiles.
我们知道他们有数以百万记的个人档案
Somebody related to him, a second cousin I would guess,
某个与他有关系的人也会在其中
would be in there.
我猜是他的从兄弟
- Sure.
- 当然
- And that was very hard to deal with.
- 这处理起来相当困难
You know, that the answer is there behind this locked door.
答案就在那里 被锁在门后
- Law enforcement is not allowed to search
执法者不被允许搜索
the databases of 23andMe and Ancestry.com
23andMe 和 Ancestry.com 的数据库
but luckily for investigators, there was another way.
但是幸运的的是 对于调查员而言 还有另一条路可走
An independent website called GEDmatch had been set up
有人建立了一个名为 GEDmatch 的独立网站
to allow people to connect with relatives.
使人们得以联系到自己的亲戚
You can upload the raw data
你可以上传自己的原始 DNA 数据
from any of the big genetic testing companies
无论它来自哪一间基因检测公司
and search for matches.
并搜索与自己基因相匹配的人
- So when we initially search the GEDmatch database,
在我们开始搜索 GEDmatch 数据库时
our best hits come back at third cousins
匹配最接近的 是他的第三代堂（表）兄妹
which means they shared you know, our top hit,
也就是说，这个人和他共享了
I think shared about 1% of the DNA.
大约 1% 的 DNA
It's very little DNA that's shared
他们共享的 DNA 确实很少
but that's a starting data point.
但这是数据的起点
And theoretically, by taking multiple of these individuals that share DNA
理论上 通过获取多个共享 DNA 的个体
and building their family trees
并且画出谱系图
using traditional genealogy and public source documents
利用传统的基因学和公共来源的文件
like census records and obituaries
比如人口普查记录 讣告
and newspaper articles and findagrave.com,
报刊文章和 findagrave.com
you build this family tree back
向上构建谱系图
until you get two of these relatives
直到在金州杀手的亲属中找到这两个人
you get them to intersect
他们最终交会在同一处
where now you see, oh, they've got,
你会发现
they share great-great grandparents together.
他们有共同的高祖父母
Theoretically the golden state killer is a descendant
理论上 金州杀手也是他们的后代
from those same great-great grandparents.
来自相同的高祖父母
So once I identify that common ancestor,
所以 一旦我确认了他们的共同祖先
it's now identifying every single descendant
接下来要辨认这对高祖父母的每一个后代
from those great-great grandparents
and this becomes a huge process.
这是个巨大的工程
People in the 1840s would typically have 15 kids.
18世纪40年代的人通常有15个子女
You have to identify each of those kids
你得逐个辨认他们的所有子女
and then all of their children
还有这些子女的所有子女
and then all of their children.
依此类推
So now we have this exponentially growing family tree.
于是 就有了一张呈指数增长的谱系图
- How wide did that tree get?
这个谱系图会变得多宽呢？
- I think we had over 1000 individuals in that family tree
我认为 里面有一千多人
but we knew a lot about our offender.
但我们对这个罪犯十分了解
We were confident he was born between 1940 and 1960.
我们确信他生于 20世纪40年代 到 60年代
We knew he was a white male.
他是白人男性
We knew he was 5'8" to 5'10".
他身高介于 5英尺8英寸(1.73m) 和 5英尺10英寸(1.78m) 之间
You know, he's in California.
你也知道 他人在加州
He's up in Sacramento in 1976.
1976年时 他在萨克拉门托
He's in Southern California in the '80s
20世纪80年代时 他在南加州
and we basically narrowed it down to about five males
我们最终将目标范围缩小到五个男性
and then it's just investigations.
然后就是调查了
- With a suspect at their fingertips,
嫌疑人已经触手可及
this spring, they followed him
今年春天，他们跟踪他
to a Sacramento area Hobby Lobby store
前往萨克拉门托的 Hobby Lobby store
and took a DNA sample from his car door handle.
并从他的车门把手上采集到了他的 DNA 样本
Days later, investigators recovered another DNA sample
几天后 调查人员找到了另一份 DNA 样本
from one discarded tissue which registered a match
是从一张丢弃的纸巾上获得的
to DNA evidence left at one of the crime scenes.
它与其中一处犯罪现场遗留的 DNA 痕迹吻合
- Investigators in California say DNA evidence led them
加州的调查人员说  DNA 痕迹引导他们
to one of the country's most notorious serial killers.
找到了美国最臭名昭著的连环杀手
Former police officer Joseph James DeAngelo was arrested yesterday
前警官 约瑟夫-詹姆斯-德安杰罗 昨天被捕
and he is believed to be the so-called golden state killer.
据信 他就是所谓的“金州杀手”
For 44 years, countless investigators have worked it
44年来 无数的调查员致力于破解此案
and have failed to solve it.
无一成功
Within four and a half months, a team of six were able
而一个六人小组，仅用四个半月
to figure out who the golden state killer was
就能找出金州杀手其人
and that was Joseph DeAngelo.
原来是约瑟夫-德安杰罗
- After the golden state killer was identified,
金州杀手被找到以后
the flood gates opened and we were seeing every week
如闸门打开一般 我们每周都能看到
not only single killers, but multiple killers, serial killers
不只单人杀手 还有多人杀手 连环杀手
every week were being identified
每周都有新的凶手被辨认出来
from cases in the '70s and the '80s.
那些七八十年代的悬案得以破解
- 'Cause, there's been over 70 cases now
因此，调查人员现在用这种方式
that they've solved this way
解决了超过70件案子
and they continue to solve them at a fairly regular rate
并且他们依然以一种相当稳定的速率解决案件。
and I think
并且我认为
- Presumably that rate's just gonna increase.
很有可能这一速率只会增加
- Yeah.
是的
- And there's gonna be more because it's working
并且将会有更多，因为这种方法是有效的
and we are going to help find these people.
我们将会帮忙找寻这些人
- But the scary thing is in the US,
但是可怕的是
you have 100,000 cold case murders with DNA.
全美一共有100000起留有DNA的谋杀悬案
You have more cold cases but the ones with DNA
总计的谋杀悬案有更多
is estimated about 100,000
但是留有DNA的估计在100000起左右
There's roughly about 650,000 sexual assaults,
大约有650000起留有DNA的性侵犯悬案
cold cases with DNA. - With DNA?
留有DNA？
It seems like a real paradigm shift.
这似乎像是真正的范式转变
- It is.
它确实是
Multiple law enforcement agencies has said
许多执法部门认为
that this is the most revolutionary tool they've had
这是他们继采用指纹之后
since the adoption of the fingerprint.
用过的最具革命性的工具
- With traditional DNA, it required getting a sample
对传统DNA技术来说，它需要从实际个体
from the actual individual.
获取样本
It's a one-to-one type of process.
这是一种一对一的过程
And so these offenders who let's say
所以这些罪犯
they have committed crimes and haven't been caught
假设他们犯了罪且从未被抓
and they're just living their life and they're thinking,
之后他们过着自己的生活，心里想着
well, my DNA has never been taken from me.
我从来没被提取过DNA
I may have left DNA in the case
我可能在1975年犯下的案子里
that I committed back in 1975,
留下了我的DNA
but they've never gotten my DNA, they won't find me.
但是执法部门没有我的DNA，他们找不到我的
But now we don't have to rely upon that.
但是现在我们不必依赖传统DNA技术了
Somebody distantly related to that offender
如果罪犯的某个远房亲戚
has put their DNA into a database
将自己的DNA录入数据库中
and they have to start getting nervous
罪犯就不得不开始紧张了
because that's outside of their control.
因为这件事不是他们能控制的
They can't account for a third cousin
他们无法了解第三代堂（表）兄妹的情况
or what that third cousin is doing.
也不知道第三代堂（表）兄妹在做什么
And so they start getting nervous.
所以他们开始紧张不安
And I've kind of wondered
我有些好奇
how many of these individuals recognize
这些罪犯中有多少人会意识到
that law enforcement is eventually gonna
因为第三代堂（表）兄妹将他们自己的DNA放入数据库
be knocking on their door as a result
最终会导致执法者
of a third cousin putting their DNA in the database?
敲响他们的房门
- Each person who uploads their information to a database
每个将自己信息上传数据库的人
illuminates the identities
将点亮他们周围
of hundreds of other people around them,
数百个人的身份
parents, siblings, aunts, and uncles and cousins.
父母、兄弟姐妹、姑姑、叔叔和堂兄弟姐妹们
A study by ancestry DNA found the average person in the UK
一项对祖先DNA的研究发现，
has 175 third cousins and it doesn't stop there.
英国人平均有175个第三代堂（表）兄妹，而且还不止于此
The DNA in one person will be shared
一人身上的DNA
by hundreds of people yet to be born.
将共享给数百个尚未出生的人
Children, grandchildren, nieces, and nephews,
子女、孙子女、侄子/孙女、外甥/外甥女
and cousins once or twice removed.
甚至是差一个或者是两个辈分的表亲
Realistically, each person shares identifiable DNA
现实中，每个人都与过去与未来的近1000人
with nearly 1000 people past and future.
共享可被识别的DNA
So it doesn't take many people uploading their data
不需要许多人上传他们的数据
to reveal the identities of everyone living in a country.
就能显示出生活在一个国家的所有人的身份
Back in 2018, a study found that using an existing database
在2018年，一项研究发现
of just 1.3 million people, they could identify 60%
使用现存的130万人口的数据库，
of all Americans of European descent.
他们能够确认出60%的欧裔美国人
And they estimated with a database containing
他们仅仅是用包含了人口总数的2%的数据库
just 2% of the population, you could find a third cousin
进行估计，就能在99%的测试例中找到
or closer match in 99% of cases.
第三代堂（表）兄妹或者更亲的血缘关系
- DNA storage is one of the things that we have
我们拥有的DNA存储
that is really unlike anything else.
和其他东西完全不同
If you look inside, this is at minus 20 degrees Celsius.
如果你向里面看 它处在零下20摄氏度的环境中
- That keeps the DNA good for a long time?
这种方法能长期保存DNA吗
- We have DNA samples in here
我们的样本
that are probably about 15 years old.
有些可能在此保存了大约15年
- How many samples are stored in there?
这里面有多少样本
- Just over 2 million.
略多于两百万
- Wow. - Yeah.
- 哇哦 - 是的
So the capacity is just over 2 million.
这个样本库的容量就在两百万左右
- 2 million people's DNA stored in this one small room?
- 你们在这个小房间里放了两百万人的DNA
- Correct.
- 完全正确
- Wow.
- 哇哦
By 2021, over 30 million people worldwide
截止2021年 世界范围内有超过三千万人
have taken a direct consumer genetic test,
参与了直接面向消费者的基因检测
the majority of which are through Ancestry and 23andMe,
他们之中的大多数经由 Ancestry 和 23andMe 进行检测
which do not currently work with law enforcement
这两家机构目前还没有与执法者达成合作
but Family Tree DNA does.
而 Family Tree DNA 相反
- If you ask Americans, should we have a national database
- 如果你问美国人 我们该不该有一个国家数据库
where everyone's logged in it?
把所有人都录入进去
- As their DNA?
- 用他们的 DNA
- Yeah by their DNA and their name,
- 是的 用他们的 DNA 和姓名
most Americans will be somewhat uncomfortable
多数美国人会对此感到不适
or potentially very uncomfortable with that.
或者在心里觉得相当难受
But we're kind of sleepwalking into that scenario.
但我们正在不知不觉中步入这样的境地
- There are some people who are concerned with privacy.
有些人对他们的隐私相当关切
If anyone chooses or decides
如果某些人选择
that they do not want their results
不允许执法者使用其结果
to be used for law enforcement matching,
进行相关匹配
they can remove themselves from that.
他们可以把自己从(数据库)中移除 *这个地方好像没有上下文
- I do worry about genetic information being used
- 我确实担心基因信息被用于
to discriminate against someone.
区别对待某些人
- My biggest thing is health insurance.
- 我最担心的是健康保险
I worry about if you have somebody's DNA profile
我担心如果有了某人的 DNA 资料
and some laws enacted, it gets in the wrong hands
特定的法律颁布后 它们会落入坏人之手
and they say that this person has a proclivity,
保险公司可能会说此人有罹患疾病的风险
they're headed towards Parkinson's,
他们可能更易得帕金森
they're headed towards this, headed towards that
他们更易得这种那种病
and then rates skyrocket.
然后保费猛涨
That's the biggest place that I see as a privacy concern.
我认为这是最关乎个人隐私的地方
- Once your genetic information is out there,
- 一旦你的基因信息被获取
it's out there.
它就会一直保存在那里
It's not like a credit card where you can get a new one.
这可不像信用卡 你能办一张新的
Yeah you're giving away something
是的 你是在把用途难料的事物
that you don't know what it can do.
拱手让人
- Well, yeah our information isn't ours
- 我们的信息起初
in the first place. - Right.
并不是我们自己的 - 的确
- Our information is shared.
- 我们的信息是共享的
- Yes with your relatives.
- 与我们的亲属
- Yes. - And although you may be
- 是的 - 并且即使你
adverse to this sort of thing,
厌恶这种东西
if they've already done it, if it,
如果他们已经做了检测
you know, in a way you're out there.
那么你懂的 某种意义上你已经在数据库中了
- In society today, you have very clearly had two camps.
- 当今社会已经分成了两个阵营
There are those that are very comfortable
那些非常愿意
having their genome available to be able to be searched
把自己的基因组交由执法者
for law enforcement purposes
进行相关搜索的
and there are others that are not comfortable at all
以及其他对此感到非常不适的
and that's okay.
这是人之常情
- The problem is of course,
- 问题当然是
those people who don't want theirs to be searchable
那些不想让自己可以搜索的人
could have their DNA uploaded inadvertently
他们的 DNA 其实已经被亲属
by their relatives.
不经意上传了
Do you know what I mean?
您明白我的意思吗
So like, if I don't want my DNA
所以 如果我不想让执法者搜索
to be searchable by law enforcement
我的 DNA
but my sister uploads hers, - Yes.
但是我妹妹上传了她的 - 是的
- It's almost as good as me doing it myself.
- 这和我自己上传效果几乎一样
- Right now, Family Tree DNA's policy
- 目前 Famliy Tree DNA 的政策是
is we only accept samples from law enforcement
我们只在某些情况下接受
under certain circumstances.
来自执法者的样本
It has to be a sexual assault, identification of remains,
样本只能来自性骚扰 遗体辨别
DNA recovered from the scene of a homicide.
或者从命案现场提取的 DNA
And we also do child abductions.
儿童绑架案也位列其中
So if there's a child that's kidnapped
所以如果有孩子被绑架勒索
and there's DNA evidence, we will process the DNA
并且有基因证据 我们会处理 DNA
so that they can try to find out who the abductor is.
这样执法者就可能找到绑匪
Those are the only cases that we will accept.
以上就是我们接受比对的情况
- Got it.
明白了
- Unfortunately now GEDmatch has flipped off the switch
- 不幸的是 GEDmatch 已经不再合作
and GEDmatch has actually said that you don't all have
GEDmatch 表示即使用户没有这样选择 * 怀疑英文不是这样的，我听到的是 You'll allow to ....
to have your information searched without opting in.
他们的信息也不被允许检索
- Right.
- 是的
- Was that decision by GEDmatch
- GEDmatch 的这个决定是
a direct result of this golden state killer case?
金州杀手案的直接结果吗
- No, it wasn't. - No.
- 不 不是 - 不
- Wanna tell the story?
- 想讲讲这个故事吗
- You know, it had to do with a Utah case.
- 这是一个犹他州的案子
- Where an elderly woman was playing the organ in a church.
- 一位老妇人在教堂中演奏管风琴时
- And there was an individual who broke in
- 有人破门而入
and assaulted her.
袭击了她
- But it wasn't a sexual assault, but it's a serious crime.
- 这不是性骚扰 但是仍属于严重犯罪
- I think believed, tried to strangle her
那人试着勒死她
and left her for dead.
然后逃之夭夭
I believe he thought that she was obviously dead and left.
我相信袭击者认为她看起来已经死去 就离开了
The police I believe approached GEDmatch
我相信警方与 GEDmatch 接触
because that they were concerned
是因为他们认为
that he was going to recommit other crimes.
犯罪者可能会再次作案
- But GEDmatch's terms of service said
但是 GEDmatch 的服务条款写明
they would only help law enforcement
他们只会在强奸和谋杀案件中
in cases of rape or homicide.
协助警方
- Her problem was that she didn't die.
她的案件问题在于她还活着
- 'Cause if she died then?
- 如果她死去的话 那么
- If she died it would have fit the conditions
- 如果她死去 那么这桩案件就符合情况
and then they would have uploaded the sample
警方就能上传样本
because it met the terms
因为这样符合服务条款
of service and everything. - So what happened?
- 所以发生了什么
They didn't take that case?
公司没接下这桩案子吗
- They did.
- 他们接下了
- They subsequently caught the individual
随后警方根据 GEDmatch 中的检索结果
from that search that they performed on GEDmatch.
抓到了犯罪嫌疑人
- But people within the genealogy world kinda got
- 但是做家谱分析的人们
their passions and flame saying that is stepping outside
非常愤怒 他们说这已经超出了
of what this tool should be used for
这个工具本应被使用的范围
and they ended up putting a lot of pressure on GEDmatch.
他们最终向 GEDmatch 施加了很多压力
- They flipped the switch because they got freaked out.
- GEDmatch 吓坏了 所以停止了与警方的合作 *没懂
- But at the end of the day,
- 但是到头来
it was a violation of terms of service.
这违反了服务条款
And I think ultimately led to a good thing.
我觉得这到最后反而是一件好事
Everybody got zeroed out
所有人的数据都被清零了
and then everybody gets to sign back in.
然后他们会注册回来
- Subsequently GEDmatch was sold to Verogen.
- 随后 GEDmatch 被卖给了 Verogen
- I can tell you a new user today
- 我可以说 目前的新用户
when they sign up for GEDmatch, about 73% of them
在 GEDmatch 注册时 会有约 73%
are signing up to allow law enforcement to search.
允许执法者检索数据
We're pretty happy with that.
我们对此相当高兴
- Yeah I mean, that's, it's a high number.
- 是的 我的意思是 这是个很高的数字
- It's a high number.
- 不是小数目
- And it suggests that people want that innocence.
- 这说明人们想要自证清白
- How many second cousins or third cousins do you now?
- 你知道几个从兄弟或者再从兄弟
You know what I mean?
懂我意思吗
You don't know that many of them.
你对他们不很了解
Without even knowing it, you're helping justice.
你在不知不觉中协助了正义的一方
You're helping a victim's family get a little bit of peace,
你在帮助受害者的家庭获得一点宽慰
not closure, but a little bit of peace
不是悲痛的终结 只是一点平静
and why not? - They get an answer.
为什么不呢 - 他们有自己的答案
- Partly, you could make an argument
- 在一定程度上  你可以这样认为
that if you wanna be an activist helping catch criminals,
如果你想成为一名帮助抓捕犯罪分子的热心市民
one of the best things you can do
你能做到的最好的事情之一
is encourage everyone you know to be tested
就是鼓励身边的每个人都接受DNA测试
and put in the database.
并将基因录入数据库
- Correct and you know, there are millions
- 的确  如你所知
of people who have tested at other companies
that are not working with law enforcement.
还有数百万人在不与执法部门合作的公司做了测试
And if they want to help, all they have to do
如果他们想要提供帮助
is download their raw data and they can upload it for free
into our database.
他们只需要下载原始数据  并将其免费上传至我们的数据库
- I absolutely believe in a person's right to privacy.
- 我完全相信人们的隐私权
But I also absolutely believe we have a right not
但是我也完全相信
to get murdered or sexually assaulted or it will be part
我们有权不被谋杀或性侵
having violent crimes committed against us.
否则相同的事情可能会落到我们头上
There has to be an equal balance.
这中间必须做出权衡
- That scale of my privacy has been taken
- 我的隐私天平不再平衡
because of a third cousin has been identified
因为一位女儿被谋杀的母亲
versus a mother who's talking
about her daughter has been murdered,
正在与被辨认出的我的三表弟对峙
that scale is way the hell like this.
就像这个鬼样子
- We're at a point now where in many ways technology
- 我们现在许多方面的科技
has kind of outstripped where the laws are.
已经超越了法律
I truly believe that
我真希望
ultimately this tool and the,
all the concerns with it will probably end up
这项技术和所有相关的问题
in front of the nation Supreme Court
最终都会提交给国家最高法院
and there will be a decision.
并且会有个结果
My bottom line message, if you're gonna make a decision,
我的底线是  如果你要做个判决
if there's gonna be laws restricting law enforcement to use it,
如果这事涉及到法律的制裁
make sure that you're making an informed decision
请确保你做出明智的决定
and not assuming what it is based on
而不是根据DNA、遗传学来猜测
its DNA and genetics and law enforcement
并将“罪犯”绳之以法
because it really isn't what you think it is.
因为它真的不是你想象的那样
- I gotta keep a couple of million people happy
- 从某种意义上说  我得让几百万人开心
so that I have access to the identities, kind of in a sense.
才能拥有这些基因数据
- In a sense, right? - Of millions,
- 某种意义上  对吧？
- 几百万
of hundreds of millions of people.
几亿人
- Right.
- 对
- And that's a pretty selective sample.
- 这是一组非常有选择性的样本
These are people who are willing
这是那些愿意放弃他们的信息的人
to give up their information - Give up, yes.
- 是的  放弃
- To find their ancestors. - Yeah.
- 来寻找他们的祖先  - 对
- There may be many others who are militantly private
- 还有许多其他非常注重隐私的人
but they don't get a say in the decision
但是他们对于
of whether they're gonna be searchable
是否可以被其他人的数据检索到
through that person or not.
并没有发言权
- True, that's the choice you make.
- 是的  这是你的决定
- That's the choice you don't make.
- 这是你不会做出的决定
- It's a choice you don't make but it's also
- 你也不会选择这样
it's the choice we have to make as a society,
但这也是我们作为一个社会必须做出的选择
is what's that balance.
这种平衡是什么
There is always gonna be winners and loses
在我看来
in my mind, right?
总会有赢家和输家
And I don't wanna use losers in the negative sense there
我并不想用消极意义上的失败者
but in a decision at the end of the day,
但是最终
you have to balance in my mind
关于公共安全和公共隐私
the public safety with the public privacy.
你会有个答案
- Is DuckDuckGo, is that good?
- DuckDuckGo  好用么？
- I use it.
- 我用这个
I'm a little paranoid.
我有点偏执
So it's supposed to not track you as much I guess, but yeah.
我觉得它应该会尽量不对你进行跟踪  就这样